Felix Lucka

Curriculum Vitae



Personal Information

Born in Hannover, Germany on May 23, 1985, nationality: German

email f.lucka@ucl.ac.uk homepage felixlucka.github.io

Research Interests

Theoretical Inverse problems, Bayesian inference, variational regularization, compressed sensing, mathematical modeling

 $\label{eq:MCMC} \mbox{Methodical} \quad \mbox{MCMC, convex optimization, numerics of PDEs}$

Applications Biomedical imaging and computing, brain research

Work Groups

- since 2014 **Member of "The Center for Medical Image Computing"**, Department of Computer Science, University College London, supervisor: Prof. Dr. Simon Arridge.
 - 2013 **Research Visit to UCLA**, *Department of Mathematics*, invited by Prof. Dr. Andrea Bertozzi and Prof. Dr. Stanley Osher.
- 2010-2014 **Member of "Workgroup Imaging"**, Institute of Computational and Applied Mathematics, University of Münster, headed by Prof. Dr. Martin Burger.
- 2008-2014 Member of "SIM-NEURO: Stimulation, Imaging and Modeling of NEUROnal networks in the human brain", Institute for Biomagnetism and Biosignalanalysis, University of Münster, headed by PD Dr. Carsten H. Wolters.

Five Key Publications

- [1] S.R. Arridge, P. Beard, M.M. Betcke, B. Cox, N. Huynh, F. Lucka, O. Ogunlade, and E. Zhang. Accelerated high-resolution photoacoustic tomography via compressed sensing. *accepted for Physics in Medicine & Biology*, (arXiv:1605.00133v3), 2016.
- [2] S.R. Arridge, M.M. Betcke, B. Cox, F. Lucka, and B. Treeby. On the adjoint operator in photoacoustic tomography. *accepted for Inverse Problems*, (arXiv:1602.02027v2), 2016.
- [3] M. Burger and F. Lucka. Maximum a posteriori estimates in linear inverse problems with log-concave priors are proper Bayes estimators. *Inverse Problems*, 30(11):114004, 2014.
- [4] F. Lucka. Fast Markov chain Monte Carlo sampling for sparse Bayesian inference in high-dimensional inverse problems using L1-type priors. *Inverse Problems*, 28(12):125012, 2012.
- [5] F. Lucka, S. Pursiainen, M. Burger, and C.H. Wolters. Hierarchical Bayesian inference for the EEG inverse problem using realistic FE head models: Depth localization and source separation for focal primary currents. *NeuroImage*, 61(4):1364–1382, 2012.

The electronic version of this document contains hyperlinks to institutions, persons and further explanations, e.g., about terms and details of the German academic system.

PhD Thesis

Title Bayesian Inversion in Biomedical Imaging

Supervisors Prof. Dr. Martin Burger and PD Dr. Carsten H. Wolters

Reviewers Prof. Dr. Martin Burger, Prof. Dr. Samuli Siltanen and PD Dr. Carsten H. Wolters

 $Sub./Defense \quad Dec.\ 2014\ /\ 23.01.2015$

Degree summa cum laude

Permalink http://nbn-resolving.de/urn:nbn:de:hbz:6-80359613770

Scientific Activities

Symposia SIAM Imaging Science, Albuquerque, May 23-26, 2016: *Imaging in the fast lane: in pursuit of dynamical information*

Applied Inverse Problems conference, Helsinki, May 25-29, 2015: "Bayesian Computation"

Reviewer Biomedical Physics & Engineering Express, Computer Methods and Programs in Biomedicine, Computational Statistics and Data, IEEE Transactions on Medical Imaging, IEEE Transactions on Image Processing, Inverse Problems, Inverse Problems and Imaging, Inverse Problems in Science and Engineering, Journal of Optics, Journal of the Optical Society of America A, Mathematical Problems in Engineering, NeuroImage, NeuroImage, Neurological Research

Referee German National Academic Foundation (Studienstiftung des deutschen Volkes), University of Innsbruck, Austria

Teaching

since 2015 Teaching assistant for the lecture Inverse Problems in Imaging

2013 Introductory course to Matlab

since 2012 Supervision of Bachelor and Masters theses.

2009–2010 Student tutor for an exercise for the course Stochastics

2007–2008 Student mentor for the courses Theoretical Physics III and IV

Education

2005-2011 **Studies in Mathematics with minor in Physics**, *University of Münster*, grade of diploma: 0.85 (with greatest distinction).

2006-2011 **Studies in Physics with minor in Computer Science**, *University of Münster*, grade of intermediate diploma: 1.0.

Aug. 2007 **Summer Academy**, Collective behavior in physical, biological and other many particle systems.

by Prof. Dr. Erich Runge, Prof. Dr. Philipp Maass and PD Dr. Michael Bachmann

Aug. 2006 **Summer Academy**, *Pattern Formation: Phenomena and Modeling*. by Prof. Dr. Andreas Mielke and Prof. Dr. Stefan Kehrein

1995–2004 **Secondary education (Abitur)**, Gymnasium Mellendorf, final grade: 1.0.

1991–1995 **Primary education**, *Grundschule Bissendorf*.

Awards and Scholarships

- Apr. 2014 Poster price, bbs2014, Berlin.
- Okt. 2012 Poster price, NeuroVisionen 8, Aachen.
- Apr. 2012 **Best talk in "Biomagnetism and online signal processing"**, Workshop "Innovative Verarbeitung bioelektrischer und biomagnetischer Signale" bbs2012, Berlin.
- Sep. 2011 **Research visit funding**, Funding for a two week research visit at the RTWH Aachen by the annual meeting of the DMV (German mathematical society).
- since Jul. 2011 **PhD-Scholarship**, German National Academic Foundation (Studienstiftung des deutschen Volkes).
 - 2005-2011 **Scholarship**, German National Academic Foundation (Studienstiftung des deutschen Volkes).

Experience

- since 2014 Research associate, Department of Computer Science, University College London.
- 2012-2014 Research assistant, Institute of Computational and Applied Mathematics, WWU.
- 2009–2010 **Student assistant**, Institute of Mathematical Statistics.
- 2008–2009 **Student research assistant**, Institute for Biomagnetism and Biosignalanalysis.
- March 2008 Internship, Max-Planck-Institute for Dynamics and Self-Organization, Göttingen.
- 2007–2008 **Student assistant**, Institute for Theoretical Physics.
- 2004–2005 **Alternative civilian service (Zivildienst)**, gemeinnützige Gesellschaft für integrative Sozialdienste mbH (GIS), school escort for a disabled child.

Engagement

University Students' union (Fachschaft), faculty council (Fachbereichsrat), miscellaneous faculty com-

mittees, faculty task force *Public Relations*, faculty task force *Networking*, organizer of the *Lange Nacht der Mathematik* (*Long Night of the Sciences* for mathematics), co-organizer of the awarded project *Studies an die Schulen*

the awarded project stadies an are sentiren

Gymnasium Student council (Schülervertretung), school president (Schülersprecher)

Miscellaneous Local youth council (Jugendparament der Gemeinde), miscellaneous political activities

References

Felix Lucha

Prof. Dr. Simon Arridge: s.arridge@cs.ucl.ac.uk

Prof. Dr. Martin Burger: martin.burger@uni-muenster.de

PD Dr. Carsten Hermann Wolters: carsten.wolters@uni-muenster.de

Prof. Dr. Samuli Siltanen: samuli.siltanen@helsinki.fi

London.

September 30, 2016